on the skep program I will
how will I have access that I don't use
get very much yes it's it's pretty neat
it'll just show up in our chat box and
you can just download it directly ok and
it should come out and nice quality
we're lagging a little bit here let me
just check
well yeah I'm on my fastest internet so
I'll keep that going ok ok so I just
want to say a few logistic things and
then we can start so first of all I
watched our first conversation again and
I was I can't believe how great it was I
actually learned more I think watching
it a second time than being there in the
first time yeah it was really neat and
by chance we did talk a lot about
religion stuff in the first chat so
hopefully we can get a really mmm I
guess in more detail this time around
sure I also just want to kind of affirm
I guess my value proposition of what I'm
trying to offer here I see a lot of
Engineers I don't know what kind of like
cognition engineers I don't know if
that's a word that makes sense for you
but what I'm trying to do is kind of
like expose not exposed but like to show
the diagram from within which all of
this like sense making and engineering
stuff is happening so so that's why I'm
asking kind of like simple questions to
try to get simple I'm trying to make a
nice diagram of what's happening and
I've also prepared something which I'm
calling a Socratic prayer
okay so yeah I hope you like this so
this is its prayer but it's it's totally
secular you know this is just something
it's an experiment we can do right now
and maybe it'll help diet the dialectic
that's happening right so I'll just read
what I wrote okay
in dialectic the conversation sometimes
leads itself we hope that this will
happen and we can be in a properly
submissive and receptive mood we
recognize that what we seek is not
directly within our grasp for if it were
we would already have it by attempting
to grasp it we gain the chance of
receiving it by being sincere and eager
and our efforts we will surely succeed
in time
amen amen I like that that's wonderful
excellent I'm glad you liked it and of
course feel free to use that in any way
you'd like to in the future okay great
thank you so where to begin is there
anything you want to begin with nope
well I'm open to just you initiating
things and asking questions as you see
fit okay excellent so religion that's
then the topic of the day last time we
talked about and you mentioned how there
are three big M's there's the the
metaphysics the mythos and meta psycho
technology right yeah so I guess my
first question is what would how would a
wisdom culture be different from that if
it is how would a wisdom culture be
different from that a wisdom culture
would have explicitly developed a cycle
a meta secular technology and a homing
metaphysics for it and entered into a
significant
reconstructive but respectful dialogue
with the existing cultural mythos to try
and integrate with that mythos machinery
as much as possible so a you know
classic example of this is neoplatonism
that really tries to develop the meta
second technology of dialectic then
works out a metaphysics around the
central notion of intelligibility as our
main marker of realness and then that
metaphysics is consciously and
deliberately integrated with the mythos
of the the of late antiquity pagan
mythos and then eventually gets taken up
and it gets integrated with Christian
mythos so there's those two strands a
pagan and a Christian version and
Neoplatonism later gets taken up into
Sufism as well through into Islam and
what you see is a reworking of that
mythos and a sort of a reverse
engineering of new practices ritual
practices spiritual exercises to try and
enact that integration of the
metaphysics the meta psycho technology
and the mythos you you can see that
history actually really unfolding and a
lot of people a lot of distributed
cognition putting a lot of work into it
both within individuals who are writing
and like these long you know repeated
treatises and dialogues and write with
other people and then they're also in
dialog and then there's a cross
generation this is a very very
comprehensive land on long term
long-standing project which is I think
why verse Lewis and his work basically
said that neoplatonism is sort of the
mystical spirituality of the West
because that all that work was really
dedicated to weaving those three
together explicate in it integrating it
with rational practices of overcoming
self-deception and an enhancing
meaningful connectedness enhancing
religio because that's ultimately I
think what it's all about overcoming
self-deception and enhancing religio
and they were wise enough to realize
that religio is bound up with mythos but
enacted imaginal pictures and
propositions and practices okay and am i
right to say religio is connectedness
there's something more than that well I
mean it's it's it's something it's it's
just that but it's really really
important I mean religio is what results
from successful relevance realization /
meeting through all the four kinds of
knowing so you get the you zero in on
the most relevant affordances and within
participatory knowing you zero in on the
most relevant perspectives within
perspective travel knowing and get the
right the best situational awareness and
then you zero in on the best set of
skills to learn or to apply or to
transfer within procedural knowing and
then you zero in on the best set of
inferences to make on the basis of your
propositional knowing and so religio
does all of that so that you are much
more optimally gripping of yourself like
really well connected to yourself to
other people into the world because
though that's those that sense of
connectedness through all of those tears
of kinds of knowing is what primarily
contributes to people's sense of meaning
in life and also that affords that
connectedness affords them
well the vertical affords them getting
the two things that I think human beings
most often seek the meta drives that are
pursued by the meta psycho technology
which is you know an inner optimization
a reduction of inner conflict of self
deception an optimization of
functionality and then you know a
connectedness to other people in the
world so you get that reciprocal opening
that's so important because
connectedness to what's real and having
that connectedness with as much peace of
mind meant positively not just
negatively I think is is optimal for
human being
that's why they enjoy the flow state so
much okay would you say that religio is
the experience of effective meta psycho
technology
I think I think that's to put it the
wrong way around I think we have religio
regard I think religio is indispensable
unavoidable human beings have to do have
some degree of religio or that means
they wouldn't be doing relevance
realization and then they're not
currently I think what you get when you
have a successful meta psycho technology
that is activating accessing
accelerating and accentuating your
religio that's when you get a sense of
sacredness so that's where that's what I
would say that is a sense of sacredness
hmm
yes sacredness was a big topic last time
for us that I could definitely go more
into yeah would you say that sacred I
mean it seems sacredness what is an
essential aspect of religion would that
also be true for a wisdom culture I
think so
I think wisdom cultures insofar as they
are pursuing that which you know
sacredness has a primary function it's
sort of the highest level version of
relevance realization we do it's really
optimizing and playing with it serious
play with it and then so far as
sacredness gives us that sense of peace
that sort of sense of home but also that
sense of connecting and opening up to a
reality beyond our egocentric bias right
so it has to be it has to both give us a
sense of home which is you know the most
powerful kind of sort of assimilation
machinery we need and a sense of the
numinous the sense of going through
transformation accommodation to a
reality that is beyond us that puts
demands on us
that
but also affords growth because it's not
just chaotic
I think insofar as the sacredness puts
us into those situations for its own for
their own sake
so sacredness is to basically seriously
play within the being mode with all of
this machinery for a developmental
purpose you're not trying to get any
specific goal
I mean people also have specific goals
whether they pray to the gods or things
like that but what's across the board is
what people are doing is very analogous
to what they're doing with music they're
playing with sound and salience in order
to really improve their sense of religio
and celebrate it just celebrate it but
because music is participatory is
perspectival it's procedural right it's
got all this stuff and you're just
celebrating it and in right and enjoying
it what enjoyment doesn't mean just
pleasure it means that sense of being
you know one with yourself and that one
with the world but not statically but
dynamically that's why we that's why you
need she said and life without a night
life without music would be a mistake so
music this is my primary metaphor for
sacredness and that's why music has been
so deeply and all the way back to the
Upper Paleolithic transition has been
associated with sacredness sacred
ceremony sacred drama sacred ritual it
seems to me that you know it's hard
using a lot of these terms I don't
there's lacking a lot of clarity and
English shelley's but religion is that
it seems to me like religion is the men
station and it's like the building that
has been built from the natural
evolution of religio like how religio
happened within individuals and between
groups eventually it kind of stay
civilized so that word it I come static
into a religion is that right
I think it I mean that's what many
people like Winkelman and especially not
Rossano and David Lewis Williams which
say with about shamanism it evolves that
way
I mean religion and this is religion is
bound out and it's bound up and it binds
together our biological aspects but it's
but also our cultural aspects and notice
the association between these three
words cult culture and cultivating right
those are all bound up together and so I
think when human beings became cultural
beings and when they had to make sense
out of their their make sense with their
capacity for self-awareness and in their
need to justify their behavior to others
and accept the justification of their
behaviors from others so when we get
into meaning and sort of the beginnings
of normativity that's when you get
culture and I think that's when religio
moves towards becoming something like a
religion we start to create ways of
trying to afford people being able to
understand and follow the normativity of
the meaning that we're making and so
that we we can have a common ground by
which we can evaluate and judge and each
other and reflect on each other behavior
each other's commitments I mean that
we're the only animals that have to do
that right now I had a really extra
conversation with Gregg on weeks about
this and the reason for reason and
Despero and Mercier in their book on the
Enigma reason is how how much we are the
only creatures that have to justify and
argue about our actions no other
features have to do this at all and
that's why we have such and it's because
of the mix of logos where that's that
that distributed cognition that spoken
language and that reflective
self-awareness though those are all
bound up together and religion is really
about
managing that is what Clifford gilts
called some meta meaning system it's
about managing all of that machinery so
all of our individual meaning projects
have a home have a something they sit
within that nurtures them but also
pushes them to grow and develop now
that's of course we're talking about
religion in its ideal case right we are
we have to completely acknowledge that
we have to have a balanced about this
right we have to acknowledge all the
ways in which religion could go wrong
and has hurt and harmed people
I've been harmed by religion myself
personally but we shouldn't do and this
is one of the things I sort of critical
of some of the new atheists about this
we shouldn't make this criticism
specific to religion all of our
institutions have been a source of great
you know terror and trauma the state of
course has been that the market has been
that right you know any any of these
huge systems by which distributed
cognition is constituted and regulated
can is tremendously powerful for
affording people meaning in life and the
cultivation of wisdom but also for
stupefying them accelerating their
foolishness and exploiting them therein
so I'm so when we're talking about this
I'm talking about you know religion in
an ideal case like I would be talking
about science in an ideal case science
is also you know science and technology
are bound together and they also have
done horrific and dangerous things but
so we have to play fair and honestly
about this but this phenomena and this
argument I do take seriously this
phenomena of the cultural enhancement of
religio that's what I think is at the
core of religion I think this is in
endemic and constitutive of our ability
to become a person that the cultivation
of personhood because a person is
someone who lives within a community of
distributed cognition shared meaning
making and shared structures of
argumentation and justification I mean
that's what a person
it's a creature that has moral and
epistemic status for us so just before
the the personhood when my brain is
fuzzy trying to catch up religio right
religion as mmm facilitator or home yes
facilitator and home and enhancer so
it's yeah so yeah I like that
facilitator but it's it's it's cultural
what does culture mean we have a shared
meaning making system that is not just
in our head it's enacted it's all the
four kinds of knowledge that coordinates
distributed cognition and in the
instance of religion it coordinates
distributed cognition for the sake of
enhancing all of that meaning making
machinery that is constitutive of making
human beings making making human beings
into persons a person to be a person is
to be somebody who is a meshed in
normative systems okay yeah that makes
sense I'm getting jumbled in my head
because to me so I have two different
lenses here right I have the ethos lens
which Aristotle and it only fits into
what you're saying of like the raft you
know political animal in a city doesn't
that's like a human being classic
Aristotle right but then the other side
is an under which is like earth soul and
deepest part of what we are it's it's
not actually human you know it's it's
pure light and pure love and and this
human stuff is like this external air
that we have respect
and you know it's part of our life but
but it's really all of life is to kind
of unfold that layer and kind of get
more into unity with the inner stuff
well but look let's go over to the other
side that the the the ethos side or the
ananda sites are the ananda side let's
do the ananda side so you're invoking
light right and love and the type of
love you're probably invoking is
ultimately a gothic love which is the
love that is it not not the love of
consumption or even cooperation but the
love that is creative of personhood
that's what it is that's why the
metaphor your seed even in the the
buddha will use the metaphor of the
mother's relationship for the child as
the primary metaphor for Karuna what
does a mother do with the child a mother
gives the kind of love that turns a
human being into a person and we find
persons intrinsically valuable there
that they are the pivot points of all of
our of all of our meaning making and
valuation systems and look at the light
well what the light right that's a
physical thing but you don't mean
physical you mean something like
intelligibility that which makes sense
that's with light things up and reveals
their presencing and their being you're
talking about a kind of identity with
that that's deeper than your own ego and
that's yeah definitely talking about
that but notice how that's also meshed
up with a lot of mythological language
you find the use of light standing for
intelligibility standing for being cross
culturally and you find that it's catchy
its mimetic and mimetic for for
distributed cognition that's why you use
light to talk about this inner suchness
of yourself and it's connection to the
mystery of the mourners of the world and
you didn't use a camel or apples or butt
but you might use water yeah why do you
use water why do you use light why do
you perhaps use fire but you you don't
use a table or you don't use you know
the car or a rocket ship or even
something natural right you don't use a
desert typically sometimes people do but
not very much all right so why what you
have to answer is why do you use why do
you pick those those are imaginal
they're not just images in their head
they they're images between you and the
world and between you and other people
you have to ask yourself well why do you
pick the ones you pick why do they catch
why do they resonate for you and what I
would say is they they you pick the ones
you do because they interface between
your own individual relevance
realization machinery and the relevance
realization that the community is you
belong to are trying to do that's how
that's how easy are we in on the ones
that really work for us did that help
well my personal experience kind of says
otherwise but they're basically because
there's a for me the bhagavad-gita was a
truly internal mystical spiritual
experience which had no relation to
anything around me in the world you know
so and and in fact I you know I had to
move to a totally different continent
after so so I can see where that does
fit in right it's like once it clicked
once it clicked then it's like okay now
I need to go find my people and be with
my people
yeah the insight doesn't become
institutionalized in or internal you
know in the world for you or
internalized in your psyche until it
resonates in distributed cognition and
please remember what the Bhagavad Gita
is about it's about integrating that
vertical mystical you know one minute
with the divine with one's duty which is
a normative you need to write those two
were Indians are inseparably bound
together with within the bhagavad-gita
I'm not trying to identify them I'm
trying to say that they're inseparably
bound together
yes well that the beauty I think of the
stern wisdom cultures because no it's
heart even call them a religion if you
if you look at it wisdom in Buddhism
compared to Christianity Islam Judaism I
don't even think I would use the word
religion to describe Hinduism Buddhism
you know well that's interesting because
that I mean that's part of the problem
of the word religion as you said it's
it's a it's actually a really recent
word most cultures don't have a word for
it that is anyway separate from their
sense of community or culture or you
know their their person identity they're
a group identity an individual
personhood if you take worship to be the
defining feature of religion yes then
but the problem with that is that's very
you know that that sort of limits you to
space and particular compares in time
because and and then the line between
worship and celebration and worship and
reverence is really really hard to
maintain so that's why I think if what
we mean by worship is sort of
prototypical Abrahamic worship then of
course only the Abraham religions turned
out to be a religion that but that's
just because we're being circular which
we're saying only the Abrahamic
religions are religion and because only
the Abrahamic religions have the feature
and that that's kind of useless so I
first engineer it I think what are the
perennial problems that human beings are
trying to solve and what sets of
practices Ecology's and practices do
they generate for solving and resolving
and ameliorating those perennial
problems and then what does that look
like in terms of the three M's right
that's that's that and for me anything
that is doing that and really reliably
enhancing religio for people within and
affording the cultivation of wisdom
because those two are inter penetrating
like we're talking
I call that a religion but I talk about
the religion that's not a religion
precisely because I think we need to we
need to reconstruct re-engineer and
reinvent eyo the Latin word inventio
means both to discover and to make so
reinvent EO psycho technologies and meta
psycho technologies and mythos etc that
is independent from this long-standing
heritage that we that we have from not
I don't need independent in that
discontinuous but we have to break out
of the cultural cognitive grammar that
regulates our religious or religiosity
if I can put it that way and even people
who aren't religious have religiosity
because it's bound up with a particular
axial age to world metaphysics
and a particular history the history of
nihilism is Heidegger would put it that
we have to break free from we have to
break free from that historical momentum
and we have to break free from its
attending a constitutive cultural calmer
culture cognitive grammar we have to get
new forms by which we conceive of
perceive of and act in enact our
attempts to enhance religio and
cultivate wisdom we need new forms of
that yes I think it's already happening
the one example that came into my head
was Tony Robbins and another like you
know New Age gurus Deepak Chopra you
know here's another funny thing with
with the word game-like guru now all of
a sudden there's marketing gurus ya know
there's a lot interfere yeah so we're in
this phase we're like the synthesis is
coming and and that's why it's I guess
it's confusing a lot of this stuff we're
talking about yeah doing it as it's
happening
yeah I hate people like Tony Robbins and
Deepak Chopra to be symptomatic rather
than particularly of 40 they tend to
actually I think you're right they're
trying to create a more secular version
of this precisely because they're trying
to escape that history but they actually
just tend to in many cases repeat they
just flattened and oversimplify the
mythos and the cultural cognitive
grammar rather than the deep thinking
the deep transformation and the very
deep practice both individually and
collectively that is needed to actually
overcome it so yes I agree with you
there yeah yeah yeah so I do see people
I do but I do also accept your point I
see lots of people both top-down
meanings sort of scientifically
historically you know public
intellectuals whatever that is the
intellectual deep web you know all these
communities whether they're trying to
recreate and reinvent see oh but I also
see and I'm involved with lots of people
who are doing the bottom-up stuff people
building new communities of practices
new communication practices new language
of communication and connection and
communion and and the DES is springing
up all over the place to fill the void
because many people find the oxalates
religions non-viable to fill the void
and to try and reconstruct a worldview
that is somehow consonant with our
scientific worldview but does something
that our scientific world doesn't do
which is homeless in it and afford us
the aspiration to wisdom and enhanced
meaning life because the scientific
worldview while powerful doesn't do
those important functions so lots of
people are trying to figure out right
what this new what this new mythos for
religio will be the new meta psycho
technology right
the new meaning it's got to be something
more than well-being that can't be
enough but I like sacred I think so I
think the last time yeah well I think
sacred is important because sacred
points too
we need something that right makes us
feel like we're connected to something
larger than our egos more real than our
own are sort of individual subject
subjective perspective that also
challenges and demands us to transform
in order to get some very deep truths
about ourselves and each other in the
world
yeah that's that's what we need just
well-being isn't enough the reciprocal
opening part of sacredness I totally get
now I think there's one more aspect to
it though for example I really love Jude
and it's one of those things which it
gets deeper that more I get into it and
there's a reciprocal opening there but
how do I know how do I know judo is
sacred to me versus I just really really
you know well the thing is when
something is sacred it should it starts
to be like I think we said it starts to
become so I'm you I use Corbin's
distinction between imaginary which is
just in your head and imaginal right it
becomes an image not in your head but an
image between you and the world image to
commodity is a term from my coffin
Johnson even though I'm quite critical
of their work in other ways it becomes
in an act so you like I same thing with
Tai Chi Chuan right the the way I am my
stance my orientation the way I get into
the flow of the way I connect anti-cheat
that generalizes is it becomes a
powerful portal an image that is a
continual portal right for that
reciprocal opening in many areas of my
life it starts to generalize and
so that and and I my strongest
realization for that was when I was had
been practicing for quite a while
and I was just as you said I was just
really enjoying it but my close friends
and colleagues started saying to me well
what's happening to you you're starting
to think and write differently and they
weren't seen me doing Tai Chi John they
were seeing me within an academic
context that's how when it starts to
permeate right and when it starts to act
as a parameter on all of you that
interactional space both the cognitive
interactional and the embodied
interactional that's when I think it
starts to become mythos for you it
starts to become something that is
sacred for you oh okay okay so we have
reciprocal on this as kind of the
mechanism but happens and then the
connection with or yeah with mythos
doing an active form together and and
did mythos well think about you're doing
in judo you're actually enacting all of
these different postures and ways of
thinking and seeing and being and
interacting with other human beings now
these are all image schemata that really
transform your access to yourself to
other people in the world at least if
it's pursued Safiye entually I mean and
if you're doing judo you know as it was
intended right it you know or Tai Chi
Chuan
of course it's a martial art for
self-defense but it's also meant to be a
much more profound transformation it's
supposed to be a wisdom right
cultivation practice yeah I would
actually call it a religion yes it the
way that yeah yeah it's just interesting
though right like um when we use that
word in English we don't think of oh I'm
going to the dojo and and I'm gonna
train for a couple hours but in Japan in
the places where they these come from it
really is a religion it's you know
they're very formal yeah yeah there's
rich
there's sacred space the dojo which is
like the temple right you have you have
the bearer of the tradition you have the
master who's a guide and he he or she is
not just trying to teach you they're
trying to mentor you and inspire you to
transformation right it I mean we're
again talking the ideal there's lots of
trappy dojos and right I'm not denying
any of this but but I think you're right
I mean when when judo becomes that
comprehensive way of life that's bound
up with enacted mythos and acted ritual
enacted transformation enacted getting
together communing with other people
training with other people transforming
with other people yes it's a religion
very much okay I want to bring some
truth about now well I just kind of want
to share with you my thoughts because
this has come up in this past month you
know especially with kovat 19 and like
this is an incredible time and of course
but more than that it uh someone like
it's a bit point or something like that
where it's or a lightning rod or some
everything that's happening is is being
a handstand exaggerated and exacerbated
times thousand million so for me
actually how China responded exactly how
I had expected them nervous now America
responded exactly how I expected them to
respond but the consequences of very
pronounced but what I think the main wet
and problem is now is hyper logos I
think that's really comes down to is two
logos by that I mean I don't mean in the
divine sense I'm doing like rationality
figure out your problems said of doing
your problem well so first of all I
would yeah I I wouldn't want to equate
the
with logos with rationality precisely
because as you said logos is a much if
you even look at it philosophically
going back to Heraclitus and then all
the way through the Stoics and in the
neoplatonist and plato it's it's not
it's it shouldn't be idea the idea is
that human rationality can participate
in the logos but kind of the model for
the logos isn't sort of human reason
also I guess what I where I would push
back a bit is that I think figuring out
your problems is what you're going to do
regardless and that the issue I think
what you're objecting to you is the idea
of a purely propositional form of
rationality and this is part of what
I've been trying to get people to
remember that rationality isn't just
argumentation and this is why you see
this in in Plato and in Socrates
rationality isn't just argumentation
it's not just inference you're right to
point out that rationality how I would
take it to mean is any systematic and
reliable set of practices that helps you
overcome self-deception and helps afford
enhanced connection enhanced religio
that's Rati oh that's the proper
proportioning of things think about how
that's even a perspectival term so when
you're doing mindfulness meditation for
me that's a form of rationality now you
might not say it's a form of reasoning
if by reasoning you want to say
argumentation that's fine but notice
even in Plato the debt the
exemplification of the logos isn't just
in the Socratic argumentation it's also
in the right exemplification of a way of
life Socrates represents a way of life a
way of seeing the world a way of
aspiring a way of undergoing deep and
profound self transformation a way of
being called into beauty I mean Socrates
is rational he could he claimed
many people say well Sagar use didn't
claim to know anything well actually he
did claim to know
claim to know erotica he knew his
rationality was the rationality of
knowing what to care about and how to
care appropriately and so this
engagement right with ways of being and
ways of seeing as well as just ways of
speaking and ways of inferring that's
what I'm talking about with rationality
and and and Agnes Keller and la Paulin
their brilliant work have shown that the
aspiration to rationality cannot itself
be an inferential process
you can't infer your way to becoming
more rational and so I mean what you
have to do is you have to go through
some fundamental transformations that
actually make you more rational and
wiser that involves transformation of
perspective transformation of identity
transformation of the skills you bring
to bear so I'm using rationality and
logos in that much more ancient
aspirational and comprehensive sense I
think trying to calculate our way
through our problems is what you'd be
criticizing that's how Heidegger would
put it and I I think while we should
continue to do our science we have to
bring back all these other kinds of
knowing and their attendant
rationalities so that's what I that's
how it was really I really like that and
agree with it I'm looking back in my
experience I've been living all over the
East for so many years and I maybe I can
just I hope you can help me draw out
what the problem is here it could
individual it may be its hyper
individuality that I would agree with
see so but that came up in my recent
voices with Ravi ki with my friend and
colleague Greg on reeks and I released
it actually yesterday
so here's three other m's for you that I
want to challenge right we have this
idea largely that comes out of Descartes
and about sort of reason as Mohana logic
it's something you do as a monologue
with yourself and there's increasing
evidence reason evolved to work
biologically that we actually reasoned
best in the sense of overcoming
self-deception and generating new ideas
that enhance our connectedness we do
that best in distributed cognition and
then of course there's the mono phasic
the idea that there's only one the state
of consciousness one state of identity
that you should be in in order to gain
knowledge whereas of course in the East
as you're saying it they have a
polyphasic culture this is work I'm
doing with Daniel Craig we're know
multiple states of consciousness and
multiple senses of identity and being
are really actually needed in order for
people to grow into wisdom and I think
we're coming to realize especially
within developmental science and
developmental psychology developmental
cognitive science that that's exactly
correct that's exactly correct and you
even see a highly logical and rational
systems like stoicism you have practices
designed to alter state of consciousness
alter perspective or knowing like the
view from above so you want to reject a
mono monological the monophasic and the
monolithic right that the that the mind
is right just is just propositional
knowing right that so you got to break
out of all of those and the thing about
that is individualism tends to emphasize
our version of individualism tends to
emphasize all of that but what the
empirical research is showing is that
individualist cultures are actually
poorer at detecting self-deception and
engaging in self correction than more
collective cultures collective
cultures have their difficulties -
they're not a panacea they're not a
paradise we're talking to a specific
thing here if we really want to do
better we do better when we are not
individualistically oriented
individualism now individualism and
here's the other thing right just we
have to resist the equation of
individualism which is it with a
particular view of mind and identity
with the moral notion of individual
responsibility individual responsibility
cultivated right it always has to be
cultivated it's important but we have of
course very good evidence that that
doesn't require the particular
ideological framework that we call you
know modern individualism which i think
is something we need to be a little bit
more critical of so that's I would agree
with you I think that's a deep point
that's a very deep point there's one
thing that I love one of one thing I
love most about most of these Eastern
cultures and especially their languages
in Chinese especially there are like a
dozen ways to say yes or no question
tags at thee so the typical way the
Chinese speak and also true for Thais
Vietnamese it's this is the room away
here you say a statement and then yes or
no and like it there's literally a dozen
different ways to do this in Chinese so
because I think that's one big reason
they can kind of say really well they
can stay collective because they're
always pushing for a yes or a n't or
disagreement yes and disagree is
actually okay because at least you know
that you disagree so you can still kind
of be still be together and and work
through it until you get to the
agreement it's always pushing further
towards agreement whereas English oh my
goodness I really don't like English
anymore it's there's so many opinions
and it's and it's all it's great for
poetry right and music and and this sort
of stuff but like detecting
self-deception in ourselves and others
the the Chinese and the other eight and
languages here they give give you a huge
leg up because that it's very binary and
very loyal and quick to see what's going
on you know I think that's right I think
that makes sense that you would that
you'd find that those features yeah so
the that I mean my understanding is that
there's their disagreement is understood
as opponent processing which is a
biological form of of self regulation
right where you have few systems that
are constantly acting as you know checks
and balances and pushing and pulling
each other and because then the idea is
that that's how the process of self
correction has actually created opponent
processing and so what's happening in
the West and this is you know with work
I did with Leo Ferraro is that that
opponent process and has has devolved
into a purely adversarial
winner-take-all processing where bots
file on IKEA the love of victory which
Plato argues is the biggest obstacle to
the love of wisdom the love of victory
has taken press me in a powerful way and
so the point about deal logos is to
bring back finally as Sophia as an
alternative to finally on IKEA the love
of victory and bring back instead the
love of wisdom so dialectic is to try
and reverse engineer the psycho
technology the meta psycho technology
that will bring this about and then when
you get into that state it's like a
collective flow state in which you can
you can definitely disagree but there's
a point of processing because then you
write there's both negative and positive
disagreement you can disagree with
somebody you say no and you're sort of
holding back and when we've prioritized
that barring that as oh that's
primary way but there's also the what
you might call positive to scream it
where's your at you you want to go
further or deeper a riff on what the
person has said you want to provoke
right and if and if these two are held
together as equally valuable the overall
project is can you and I get to a place
together where you couldn't get to
individually and where I couldn't get to
individually and that when that starts
to happen and we start to get a cascade
of those we start to get a flow of being
in a place where you know getting to a
place in our insight in our
intelligibility our ability to make
sense of ourselves each other in the
world if we can get to a place that we
couldn't get to individually and then
you know we're getting to flow my friend
layman Pascal calls this overflow which
is a wonderful term if we can get into
overflow I think that is where we do our
best reasoning and our best our best
transformation and we also feel at our
best we this is a way of what it feels
like this is how human beings are
supposed to live how they're supposed to
dwell with each other and on the earth
yes that's the feeling of Judo for me
yes yep judo is doing that same thing
that that dialectic flow in a physical
domain and that's all sort of i yeah
yeah go ahead
yeah well that's why that's my that's
why I brought in the Socratic prayer is
is is to its brain
you know what we're doing in that way so
we have a better way just hopefully
it'll work better that's all I do want
to say again I forgot I wanted to say
one more time though he thought sorry to
interrupt to you know I want to say
again though that I don't want to you I
wouldn't want to put on a pedestal right
collectivist cultures because they also
they're also problematic in certain ways
so
I just want I just wanted to state that
I mean that's not where the
conversations going right now so I don't
want to derail it but I don't want to be
misinterpreting on this point either
right No
so go ahead so though clear to me it's
really interesting I've never studied
prayer I've I've only done it a few
times but the one time I did it really
worked it was it was really simple an
effective process which I think for me
is better than decision so what I do is
I have an intention and I pride it or
desire even and I try to clear by it in
my mind and then I express it to the
world or to God and then let go let go
of any outcome that'll happen from that
and just repeat that process and the one
time I did it that it worked instantly
and I got into this incredible focused
state of learning which I haven't been
into since yeah there are powerful ways
I mean so prayer is biological in nature
and when so there's research showing
that when people pray so they had like
an experiment with the head people pray
to God who were believers in God versus
praying to Santa Claus in very different
parts of the brain are activated and so
prayer is a way of getting into a
dialogical mode with right with your
relationship two aspects of that are
mysterious to you of your own
unconscious and then also aspects of the
world that are mysterious to you you
know because they're the depths of the
world and what the world is
combinatorially explosive and complex
and so prayer is a way of putting you
into a dynamic sort of biological
preparedness that can really access your
relevance realization machinery and some
very very powerful ways and help to
sensitize you to well as you said to
learning to
patterns you didn't see before and
realizing things you didn't realize
before and I I don't believe in the
supernatural for lots of reasons that
I've articulated elsewhere and so on
I don't think of prayer as a key voting
supernatural forces on our behalf but I
do acknowledge that prayer can have that
effect of putting people into a powerful
state of preparedness in in perception
and in cognition that helps them see get
an answer from the world in that and
that they realize and see things they
wouldn't otherwise realize and see
that's why there's many forms of Prayer
like the centering prayer and the prayer
of the heart even with in
judeo-christian practices that are not
petitionary you're not asking for
anything you're just in fact you're just
trying to come to that state of you know
receptivity and preparedness and
openness and connectedness and as you
say focus you're sort of putting
yourself into the machinery to get into
a flow flowing a flow state with respect
to the world and hopefully a flow State
that's also you know connecting you to
new patterns that are important for the
challenge you face so yeah that's how I
would that's my take on that okay
excellent
full disclosure I've been fasting today
and I'm realizing that's why I think I'm
thinking I'm all pulled up and a little
tired but once we start did I kind of
like my badness turned on which isn't so
another important word is faith and
you're like prayer are we acknowledge II
right so I would faith fit in within
religion are the three atoms yeah yeah
well I'm having a lot of really good
discussions about this with you know
Andrew Sweeney Christopher mustard yeah
so I Jordan all I think of faith up you
know it's a it's a practice but a full
person practice that couples the
emergence of mind so I don't mean new
ideas I mean that like developmental
emerging the way an adults mind emerges
from a child's mind the emergence of
mind to the emergence of the world so
what patterns that are emerging that are
crucial for you like to zero in on is
really relevant in really mattering and
so faith in that sense is the decoupling
the wedding and I and I I mean the you
know I want to invoke the sexual
metaphor because the off the Hebrew word
for has that sexual connotation is like
sexual intercourse
right is to have you couple you Wed the
emergence of mind to the emergence of
the world so that you come into an
ongoing right relationship with the
world where right relationship means you
can follow the course of things you are
sensitive to Kairos you sensitive to how
things are turning and you're sensitive
to when you need to stand back and allow
and when you need to intervene and then
notice how this overlaps with wisdom
when you need to intervene so my model
for this and this comes out of death is
your faithfulness to your your partner
you know your romantic partner right it
doesn't mean that you have a stable set
of beliefs or that you have a complete
account of them or that you even have
sort of an absolute certainty about them
because of the fact that they are going
to change and grow what it means is you
have found a way of staying in a
continuity of contact with who they are
and how they're growing so that you can
afford
agape you can afford their growth and
you are sensitive you don't know where
it's going but you have that online
sensitivity to how they might be at a
turning point in their life or something
crucial like cross or crisis which means
judgment you're there and you can sense
what
and you got you know when to move in
when to move back
you have finesse I was talking with Paul
and clay about all of this
finesse about how to maintain that
continuity of contact so that you're
what emerges in your development right
is affording for your partner's
development that's what it is to be
faithful to someone to commit to that
because you find that connection to them
you find it ultimately beautiful for you
it strikes you as deeply good not just
morally good but deeply a good way of
being that's what I mean
yeah the example of being faithful to
like your partner is a great example I
think I've heard that one be in other
places I did your Paul event I
compeition there's one thing that that
bore its whole and well in one word it'd
be ethos so yeah as Paul was talking
this I deal person who can kind of
respond effectively to Isis any yeah II
was not sure like who is this person do
you look like how do we you know deep
this to me that's ethos and
I did say like it's easy me to say that
I've put this all well but in a very DIF
that you often like I mean I'm in one of
the best cities China in China is one of
the best countries the world to be in
right now because yeah but but um it's
team thing that I always come back in
for ethos or our character and what it
means to be a really well developed
character is we you could call
detachment or indifference so someone
who is totally beyond the crisis won't
even talk about and that's what happened
that's what I what I do that's what all
my Chinese neighbors are doing they just
don't even talk about it and they don't
romanticize the language so in these
they're they have a work or coronavirus
it's like being done it's two syllables
it's a very simple word and as far as I
know that's all they talk about it but
in do you have flatten the curve and
social distancing and Conte what is a
contract tracing oars like there's this
there's a whole new language of it
developing now and to me that's that's
the opposite way that you want to do it
the the developed character says this is
just you know this is a little like
hiccup and I'll just you know do some
breathing and then it goes away and the
opposite way is that oh my god things
going on and well I guess what I would
say about that is I agree with the the
developed character I mean but that
there's a difference right in that you
know the China has it's at all Jen
regime that was able to top-down do all
of what needed to be done the West's are
you know Western democracies we have
talk a lot about it because that's how
the government operates I you know I
well I would appeal to Aristotle to you
on this right my I think detachment
doesn't mean indifference at least not
the sense of yeah yeah they're not same
thing that so airs though you know air
so example is anger it's famously is
anger he says you know the point is not
to be angry or not angry the point is to
be angry at the right time for the right
reasons to the right degree right and I
think so I think bringing our problems
solving abilities to bear on this
individually and collectively you know
at the right time for the right reasons
to the right degree is what we should be
doing and I think that's gonna look
different for different cultures because
different cultures have organized or
organized politically and
socioeconomically differently so they
have to dispose of their resources in
different ways I do think you're right
that and I like what Jordan Hall has to
say but is he said we have to steer
between what he calls pent panic and
anti panic panic is like your time with
people right an anti panic that people
are just saying oh there's nothing there
it's a hoax it's not real we don't need
to do anything and we got to avoid both
of those I mean it's the golden mean of
Aristotle we have to find that and I
think that's the mark of good character
and that's goes back to again the person
who has the gold Amin is the person who
can stay in continuity of contact with
the situations because they don't get
polarized in two extremes so they can
stay and shift with things as they're
moving so that's that's how I would
that's how I'd respond to what you said
okay okay cool so another thing I've
been noticing this is also why I've
chosen ethos and non doesn't it's
because do all different dimensions live
on so to me that the cultural dimension
is is qualitatively higher than social
political economical
yeah well I really feel that so well
well yes we can see the Chinese system
is better equipped to handle such a
thing which it is what's really more
important is the culture so I agree with
you on staying around here is like when
it's the middle of the virus or before
after they're just they're still just
Chinese people you know they still they
it's like nothing has happened for them
because they that's their culture they
like there could be just thousands of
years of non-stop cultivation character
and whatever else they've been doing but
they just there's no panic
they don't want really telling example
of this was uh there's a video of an old
lady being you know quarantine by the
police into a van and she was saying
kill me kill me now that's really
interesting because she's being literal
she's she's not saying I can't help
saying I just uh I'm I'm over all of
this and the fact they give me any kind
of trouble it's like just kill me and
that's a very different response from me
very different Wes oh yeah I agree I
agree that the cultural level is really
important I do I think I think it is
more important than the political level
or the socio-economic level I do I agree
with you on that it's it's hard to see
some you know I don't want to go too
much into the modern event stuff oh
here's thing in my notes that I think an
interesting relate transcend since the
that whole game of like how to make
sense of the world and like and is this
fake news is this real news when you're
fully grounded and religion that process
it's not like it disappears but it it
becomes pushed down to a much like lower
level where it's not as important
anymore
does that make sense I think so I I mean
I I mean Paul Van de CLE has this
wonderful thing where he says politics
is about the now and religion is about
the always and so religion tends to put
you into the the domain of perennial
problems and perennial patterns and so
those are these are much more
comprehensive long-term bigger scope and
in that sense what we find significant
or what we find really matters are
salience landscaping really changes
that's why you do for the view from
above at the same point like it changes
you when you do the view from the bub
you see the bigger picture as we say the
bigger patterns right the things that
actually matter across time and space
more reliably and I think one of the
things that religion does is exactly
that it puts you into a participatory
contact with these bigger patterns these
perennial patterns these perennial
problems and in that sense it alters
what you care about we're back to
Socrates well you know educating what
you care about and caring about it in
the right way into the right degree and
this is Aristotle - you know he's the
grandson of Socrates right that is I
mean intellectually I mean that dad that
that's that's what I think that you're
right that and when people who live well
again when would the religion is about
well we've been talking about enhancing
religio and ameliorating self-deception
and affording wisdom then it does all of
that of course but religion can also be
a place where people go to play politics
and play socio-economic games and to
pursue ideology and to oppress other
people I mean so we again we're talking
about I know a particular way of
understanding religion in its ideal form
yeah I need to get going soon ethos
uh sorry I wanted to give you also a
chance I didn't to just end like if you
want you wanted you know sort of a
summative thing we can come to it you
know
yes yes thanks
I think that's good timing I don't know
there's too many different threads here
right so yeah something hope I hope we
can really make some kind of summary
here something about okay how about this
but just faith it sounded a lot like
connectedness today and a lot like
religio so yes tell me what do you think
how do those correlate I think faith is
a commitment to a wise way of being that
has the capacity to reliably enhance
religio mm okay Oh perfect you say that
the the lack of mythos is the one thing
that separates a wisdom culture from
widget um I don't know I think I mean
look at the example with judo oh you
called it a religion because it's very
hard to find people cultivating because
like I said it's part what's one of the
three M's right it's very hard to find
people cultivating wisdom that aren't
getting involved with mythos right mando
we talked about Neoplatonism I think the
mythos is right and mythos means not
just images it also means actions
rituals right gestures things like that
I think that you're gonna find mythos
wherever people are aspiring to you know
comprehensive transformation and
training
because that's the only way to access a
lot of this machinery it's like what
we're talking about with prayer it's
there's certain ways of being or that
that's how we access both you know
within you know the levels of the psyche
and within the levels of the world
that's the only there's ways the you
know there are indispensable to us in
accessing those those levels and that's
where mythos those enacted imaginal
patterns are just indispensable to us I
I think the difference is between a
wisdom tradition and religion and if we
want to make a distinction I think the
only place you're going to be able to
make a distinction is when you're again
where we're back to making worship the
defining feature of religion rather than
the cultivation of wisdom and and then
again I think we're back to the
circularity of what we're just only the
Abrahamic religions are religions which
okay if that's what you want to do but I
don't know that does I don't have that
does this any good no that's um it sheds
light on it I think good good great
thank you again for talking with me John
it was good appreciate it
yeah I look forward to to doing another
one of these and I like you know I like
the way you keep trying to get it you
know very sort of concrete and specific
I think that's very very helpful and I
like the way we we had a lot of good you
know back and forth I think it was
really excellent so thank you you
thought I really enjoyed it a lot thank
you okay great so it's a probably about
lunchtime for you yeah yeah I'm gonna go
get something to eat yeah okay cool
enjoy your lunch and I'll see you soon
okay take care
mmm take care bye bye